This lecture will be split between memory consistency and SIMD architectures.
We will first continue exploring shared memory multi-processors
and discuss the concept of sequential consistency, then we'll get back to Flynn's taxonomy and cover
SIMD and MISD parallel systems. Let's start by distinguishing between two terms,
cache coherence and memory consistency. Coherence pertains to the ordering of multiple cores or
multiple threads, reads and writes to a single memory location. As discussed last time, enabling
coherence implies that all accesses to a single memory location are ordered as if they were performed
in some sequential order. On the other hand, memory consistency pertains to the ordering of
multi-threaded reads and writes to all physical memory locations. The most intuitive consistency
model is sequential consistency, which like coherence enforces that accesses to all memory
locations are ordered as if they were performed sequentially. This is the easiest model for
programmers to understand, but like in-order cores, this can greatly constrain performance when
threads want to read and write different memory locations that have no relation or dependence
to one another. Instead, many modern systems employ relaxed consistency models that allow
some reordering to happen so that we can improve performance. We'll only be discussing sequential
consistency in this course. Relaxed consistency is left for advanced courses.
Sequential consistency is met with two properties that we want to uphold. First, we want to enforce
intra-thread program ordering of memory accesses so that each individual cores reads and writes
occur in the order specified by the programmer. This means that even though memory addresses
x and y point to different memory locations, we need to make sure that a load from x happens
before a store to y, since that's what the programmer specified. Second, we want to enforce
serialization of all reads and writes across all threads. As shown, this can be viewed as
effectively having a single arbiter that allows only one core to access memory at any moment.
If our multiprocessor system upholds these two properties, then we can say that our system is
sequentially consistent. Now let's go through some sequential consistency examples and show how
even simple optimizations in our compiler and architecture can actually violate SC.
Let's consider this example multi-threaded program running on two cores. If we assume that
the two shared memory locations x and y are both initialized to zero, if our system were
sequentially consistent, would it ever be possible for both a and c to be equal to zero at the end
of the program? No, if you walk through all the cases, you'll find that it is not possible for
a and c to be equal zero. If a ends up being zero, then p1 must have executed both instructions
before p2 stores five to y. This is because a can't get zero without x getting eight. Continuing on,
that means that p2 must read the value of eight for x when it computes c, so it's not possible for c
to also equal zero. On your own, walk through what a would be when c was zero.
However, there's a very common compiler optimization typically made called common
sub-expression elimination. The compiler is smart enough to recognize operations that are identical,
such as this x times two computation. So if the compiler performs common sub-expression
elimination, the compiler will simply replace the computation of c with b so that it doesn't do any
redundant ALU work. Unfortunately, though, this seemingly harmless optimization actually violates
sequential consistency. This eliminates the second load of extra memory, and now it is possible for
both a and c to end up being zero. Let's look at another example. If you were to go through this
program, you'd find that it is impossible for all of a, b, and c to be equal to two at the end of the
program. In fact, it isn't even possible for either a or b to be equal to two in the end.
Please pause, walk through this, and confirm your understanding.
But as you might expect, simple compiler optimizations may end up compromising sequential
consistency. As before, common sub-expression elimination may be employed, replacing the
second load of x with just a copy of the value and variable a. And then, since b is now directly
being set to a, it seems obvious to the compiler that this if statement is always going to be true.
So if it's always true, then we can just remove the branch entirely, saving some cycles and
potentially avoiding mis-speculation. But now that we're left with just these three instructions,
in the compiler's mind, the store to y has no data dependence with the previous two instructions.
So our compiler may feel free to move the store to y earlier. And now, if we were to go through
this optimized program, which seemingly performs the same computation as before,
we'd find that sc can be violated, and indeed, all a, b, and c can equal two at the end of the program.
Let's look at how our hardware optimizations can also affect consistency.
In this program, it's clear that the assertion in p2 should never be false,
because p2 would not enter the if block unless y were not zero. And looking at p1's code,
y can only be set to one after having set x to one as well.
However, without of order execution and branch prediction, it's possible that the load of x
and p2 can finish executing before the load of y in the branch condition. For example,
p2's load of y may be a cache miss. But due to branch prediction, we may proceed and execute
the load of x, which may be a cache hit. Then by the time we finally get the data for y,
it's possible that y may have been set to one. Thus, the branch prediction is deemed correct,
even though we have read an older value of x.
In this case, the assertion fails and sc is violated.
Finally, we'll look at a more complex example with three threads running on a multiprocessor.
p0 effectively sets the flag y that allows p1 to continue,
and p1 sets the flag z that allows p5 to continue.
In the end, it is not possible for b to read the value zero.
But let's consider what happens when running these threads on a real multiprocessor,
where the cores are interconnected by some network. This means that for p0,
p1 is closer than p5. Thus, coherence messages get delivered to it in less wall clock time than
they do p5. So let's see how that affects the program.
Say the first thing that happens is p0 stores to x, and this value properly gets propagated to p1
and p5's caches, as shown. Now assume that network congestion has built up in the system
between p3 and p4 due to some unrelated programs. So now when p0 stores to y,
p1 is made aware of this change immediately, while p5 still has no idea that the change
has happened due to the congested network link. Then, since p1 is already aware of the modification
of y, it now breaks from the while loop and continues executing its instructions and performs
a store to z. Because its path to p5 is not congested, p5 notices the change to z before
it notices the change to y. And because of that, we now end up with an impossible scenario of b
being set to zero, violating sc. So how do we provide sequential consistency while allowing
ourselves to benefit from these optimizations? The key is that to achieve sequential consistency,
it only needs to look like these properties hold. To maintain intra-thread program order,
we can tell the compiler specifically which loads and stores should not be optimized and
reordered, while the rest can still be optimized freely. This applies to the first two examples
earlier and can be done using the volatile declaration in the program code. To account
for hardware optimizations like the out-of-order execution and branch prediction in the third
example, we can apply a mechanism of load replay, where we allow loads to be performed
out of program order, as long as we double check them in order upon retirement. And finally,
if we don't want to have to change our out-of-order hardware implementation to support replay,
the programmer can manually insert fences to stall younger memory operations and force program
ordering. Now, for inter-thread serialization, we recognize that we don't actually have to
serialize reads across threads because they don't modify any values, so they can happen in parallel.
So if that's the case, then inter-thread serialization can be simplified to just
inter-thread write atomicity, that is, all writes are globally serialized. And to do this,
we need to make sure that all writes are made visible to all cores atomically,
and we leverage the cache coherence protocol to do this. If one core modifies a block, we just need
to make sure that our protocol waits for all other cores' acknowledgment of the modification
before we're allowed to proceed. We'll discuss each of these four mechanisms in a bit.
The first mechanism is to use volatile declaration, which allows programmers to
tell the compiler that a memory location may potentially be modified by some other thread or
entity. So in this example, if memory address x is declared volatile, the compiler must assume
that loads to x may not return the same value each time as it could be getting updated by a
different thread. Thus, the compiler can't simply set b to equal to a, because during the time in
between the two instructions, x may have been modified externally. This forces the compiler
to be conservative and follow the programmer's explicit instructions and not optimize nor
reorder memory loads and stores for this address. So applying this to example two from earlier,
we force the compiler to keep all the instructions the way they're written. With this, it is now
impossible to have a, b, and c all equal to, which means no sc violation.
The second mechanism was replay. We need to make sure that despite out-of-order execution,
memory accesses in my thread should appear to execute in the order that they were specified
by the program. This is no problem for stores, because as you recall from our discussion of MIPS
R10K, stores are performed in order at retire instead of during execute. So we only need to deal
with the loads, but we don't want to lose the benefit of executing loads out of order, since
they can be very expensive, especially on a cache miss. So the idea is to go ahead and let loads
execute out of order, as long as we replay the load again when it retires, just to make sure
that the value has not changed since then. If it has changed, then we need to flush and re-execute
all of the instructions that were dependent on the load. So in the example below, it is possible
that the younger load may actually execute before the older load. This can violate sequential
consistency if we weren't allowed to read the younger load's value before the older one.
So to make sure there are no issues, we need to replay the younger load when it eventually
retires. This makes sure that the value hasn't changed since then. And this extra load operation
is generally not expensive, since by the time we get to retire, the load value is most likely
still in the cache, so it incurs minimal performance overhead to replay the load.
So now we can apply this replay mechanism to example 3. With branch prediction and out of
order execution, we will still let the load of x execute first, potentially reading the
stale value as 0. But that's okay, because by the time this load retires, we will get the proper
value of 1 since the load of y must have retired and returned 1 by now. Thus with replay, it is
impossible for a to be equal to 0. One way to enforce intrathread ordering of loads and stores
without changing the out of order hardware is to insert memory fences or memory barriers into
the program. A general memory fence, denoted M fence here, ensures that all earlier loads and
stores in this thread must be completed before any loads and stores are allowed to execute.
This is a fairly severe constraint, and often it's sufficient to just have a fence for either loads
or just stores. So a load fence stalls any future loads or stores to any address until
all prior loads have retired. And a store fence stalls any future loads or stores to any address
until all prior stores have been retired. So going back to example 3, we can ensure that
sequential consistency is not violated by inserting appropriate fences. In P1, we insert a store fence
to make sure that the store to address x completes before the store to address y is allowed to be
executed. And in P2, the load fence makes sure that the load of y completes before the load
of x is executed, thus preventing the SC violation. The last mechanism is coherence acknowledgments.
We need to make sure that when a core modifies a value and transitions to the M state,
all other cores first need to acknowledge this action before any core is allowed to read the
new modified state. Note that for the snooping-based coherence implementations that we focus on in
this course, it is implied that these writes are atomic since we're using a common atomic bus,
and we assume that all cores are consistently watching and snooping the bus.
However, if we didn't have a common atomic bus, here's what the coherence protocol would
support to ensure right atomicity. When y is modified by P0, the congestion between P3 and
P4 may slow down the notification to P5. But by ensuring that all nodes have to first acknowledge
the write, then P1 will not be allowed to read the new value of y just yet.
Only until P5 has acknowledged receipt of the notification will both P1 and P5 see the new
value of y, which is 3. Only after that is P1 allowed to proceed and modify the value of z.
But by the time P5 sees the modification of z, it is guaranteed to have seen the modification of y,
ensuring sequential consistency is not violated.
All right, that wrapped up our discussion on shared memory CMPs,
which was our main focus for MIMD parallel systems. Let's return to Flynn's tectonomy
to briefly cover the other paradigms, SIMD and MISD.
In general purpose processors, SIMD parallelism takes the form of vector, or superword,
instructions. The idea is to perform a single operation on multiple sets of data registers
in parallel. In the example shown here, we have a vector add instruction that is able to add four
registers with four other registers and write the result into four distinct registers, all as a single
instruction. To support vector instructions, the ISA needs to support vector registers.
Generally, vector registers are composed of multiple regular registers. For example, shown here,
vector register A can consist of four regular registers R0, R1, R2, and R3.
These are registers can be used individually as operands for regular instructions.
But to perform a vector operation, the program must first put all of its operands into one of
the vector registers A, B, or C. In Intel's SSE vector instruction set, there are eight 128-bit
vector registers that can be accessed as two 64-bit registers, four 32-bit registers, eight 16-bit
registers, or 16 8-bit registers. To take advantage of vector instructions, the compiler
usually employs two techniques, loop unrolling and loop fusion. Loop unrolling combines multiple
iterations into a single larger loop body. If all of the instructions in the loop body are
performing the same operation, there are four ads in this example, then the instruction can be
converted into a single vector instruction. In this example, this can approach a speed up of four
by vectorizing every four loop iterations. Loop fusion, on the other hand, merges multiple
independent loops together into one larger loop. And if all the instructions in the loop body are
performing the same operation, then they too can be replaced with a single vector instruction per
iteration. Here we compare and contrast vector, or superword level, parallelism versus instruction
level parallelism, which is the form of parallelism exploited by superscalar out-of-order processors.
The downside of vector instructions is that the program first needs to move their data into
dedicated vector registers. Then after executing the vector instruction, the results need to be
moved to their intended destinations. This is known as register packing and unpacking,
and can incur significant performance overhead. Further, vector instructions are less flexible
since the same operation needs to be done for all operands. On the other hand, instruction level
parallelism fetches and executes more total instructions. In the example shown, even though
i1, i2, and i3 are independent and can be executed in parallel, we still need to fetch and execute
three instructions and occupy three spaces in the ROB and other hardware structures. The advantage
of vector instructions is that multiple operations are encapsulated as one single instruction.
This is why the hardware complexity of vector instructions is much lower than a superscalar
out-of-order core. So to make the hardware cost of a superscalar processor worth it,
it needs to be utilized as much as possible by the program. If the program has too many dependent
instructions, then the hardware cost may not be worth it. As an analogy, vector instructions are
like a buy one, get one free deal. The discount is less flexible and is only really useful if you
plan on buying multiple of the same product, whereas implementing a superscalar processor is
like a membership discount. It's more flexible, but it imposes a high base cost and needs to be
well utilized in order to be worth this cost. Building on the SIMD principle is the notion
of single instruction multiple threads parallelism or SIMT. GPUs are the popular choice for SIMT
execution. They were originally designed as shader cores for graphics programs where
tons of threads are needed, and the threads basically all perform the same computation but
on different data. And for the most part, each thread's computation did not have complex flow
control and was just performing a bunch of arithmetic on its data. Today GPUs are effectively
general purpose, being used for a broad range of applications, not just graphics.
The high level architecture of a GPU revolves around three key assumptions. The first is that
all threads perform the same computations. If that's the case, then we can have a single set
of fetch and decode logic for an entire group of threads. Think of it as a very wide superscalar
machine with simultaneous multithreading of, say, 32 threads at a time that all run the exact
same instruction on every single cycle. We're able to densely pack all of these threads into a
single processor by fetching and decoding for all 32 threads at a time. We just need to have
enough ALUs and registers for all the threads. The second assumption is that the GPU program,
commonly called a kernel, is expected to run many threads. The idea is to stamp out
many of these streaming multi processors, as they're commonly called, and implement a scheduler
that manages placement of the threads. The last assumption is that each kernel is expected to run
many, many threads, way more than the number of hardware threads that the GPU supports.
The idea is that whenever a group of threads gets a cache miss or some form of stall event,
the scheduler is able to context switch in another group of threads to immediately start executing.
This ensures that the GPU pipeline is always utilized and hides the delays of cache misses
and other stalls. The last parallelism paradigm is MISTI, or multiple instruction single data.
This can be viewed as the transpose of vector execution, where many different operations
are simultaneously performed on a single piece of data. This concept is shown here where the
streaming MISTI architecture processes one data element at a time, which propagates through a
series of instructions. This has historically been a less common paradigm, but is gaining more
interest lately for big data computing, where lots of data needs to be processed and data
reuse is generally low. Let's wrap up and work through an exercise on sequential consistency.
Given the program from example four earlier, if our hardware and compiler does not implement SC,
where should we insert the minimum number of load and store fences to guarantee
sequentially consistent execution? Assume that the coherence protocol enforces
inter thread write animicity. Please pause and work this out.
Okay, so to ensure sequential consistency, this set of dependencies needs to be enforced in the
program. P1 needs to wait for y to be set before it loads x, and P5 needs to wait for z to be set
before it loads y. z can only be set by P1 after y has been set. Write animicity ensures that the
inter thread dependence between P0 and P1 and the dependence between P1 and P5 are enforced.
Sequential consistency can only be violated if instructions within each thread are reordered.
In this machine, there's no guarantee that P0 writes to x before it writes to y,
so there's no guarantee that P1 reads y before it accesses z and x, and there's no guarantee that
P5 reads z before it reads y. If you didn't get this before, and now you think you've got the
right hint, please pause and fill in the blanks. All right, to ensure proper program ordering,
we need to insert a store fence in P0 to maintain ordering between assignments to x and y,
a load fence in P1 to ensure we've loaded the non-zero y before we load x,
and a load fence in P5 for the same reason as P1. Note that no fence is needed between the store to
z and the load of x and P1 since these do not need to be ordered in any particular way. They'll
still be sequentially consistent as long as both happen after the load of y.